NAVEEN N RAVICHANDRASEKARAN

250 East 6th Street, Apt 0402 \$\infty\$ Saint Paul, MN 55101

(832) · 720 · 2393 ♦ http://www.naveenravichandrasekaran.com/ ♦ nravi.research@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focus on the following areas: (i) parallel programming models and runtime systems (MPI and Partitioned Global Address Space models like OpenSHMEM, Global Arrays, and Coarray Fortran); (ii) parallel computing architectures (Cray Supercomputers and Clusters, multi-core systems, GPUs and Intel MIC), and (iii) high-speed interconnect libraries(DMAPP)

EDUCATION

University of Houston, Main Campus

December 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

May 2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

EXPERIENCE

Cray, Inc

12/26/2015 - Present

Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Software Enhancements and Parallel Optimizations for Cray Supercomputer and Cluster environments
- · Work specifically on Cray software stacks like Cray MPI, Cray SHMEM, and Global Arrays
- · HPC and parallel programming runtime optimizations for Cray hardware to be utilized by specific customers like U.S government and commercial petroleum industries
- · Participate and represent Cray in OpenSHMEM standards committee

Cray, Inc

05/18/2015 - 12/25/2015

Intern - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Research, Prototype, and Implement new features in Cray SHMEM programming library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

University of Houston

09/14/2013 - 05/15/2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Dr.Barbara Chapman(Chair, Computer Science & Mathematics(CSM) Group Brookhaven National Laboratory)
- · Research and explore strategies for runtime optimizations, and compiler-tools interactions for large-scale parallel systems using OpenSHMEM and Coarray Fortran programming models

Cognizant Technology Solutions

06/23/2011 - 07/12/2013

Programmer Analyst

Chennai, India

· Design parallel test framework to validate bank statements for a leading financial services company

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages
Parallel Programming Models
Network Libraries
Architectures

C/C++, Fortran, Java, Python, Ruby, Scala OpenSHMEM, MPI, Coarray Fortran, OpenMP DMAPP, Verbs, Libfabrics Cray Supercomputers, & Clusters, Intel MIC

Current Projects

1. Cray OpenSHMEMX

- Cray OpenSHMEMX is a new SHMEM library implementation developed to supersede the existing production ready Cray SHMEM library on future exascale Cray architectures
- Design and develop Cray OpenSHMEMX from scratch with support for different transport layers including DMAPP, XPMEM, and Libfabrics
- Provide complete backward compatibility with Cray SHMEM with all Cray specific features

2. Cray SHMEM

- optimize and maintain Cray SHMEM a production quality SHMEM library implementation for different Cray platforms
- implement new features as per the OpenSHMEM standards
- propose and prototype new features like Communication Contexts, Symmetric Memory Partitions and Teams(PE-Subsets)

3. Cray MPICH

• create an optimized message matching layer for the MPI implementation.

Past Projects

1. Cray Global Arrays(Cray-GA) optimize and maintain the ComEx - DMAPP communication layer

2. OpenSHMEM Reference Implementation

Project description: University of Houston worked with *Oak Ridge National Laboratory* to standardize OpenSHMEM via a community-driven specification with a reference implementation. **My contributions:** I have been particularly involved in the optimization of the collective communication performance.

3. Coarray Fortran

Project description: Coarray Fortran is a set of new language features incorporated into the Fortran 2008 standard which enable parallel programming in Fortran with minimal changes to the language syntax. It is a joint project between University of Houston and *Total* **My contributions:** I am particularly involved in the optimization of the Coarray Fortran runtime library with new underlying communication layers.

REFEREED CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

- 1. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, D.Pou, and M.Pagel. "Introducing Cray OpenSHMEMX A Modular Multi-Communication Layer OpenSHMEM Implementation.". In Proceedings of Fifth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies, August, 2017, Hanover, Maryland, USA.
- 2. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, Maryland, USA.
 - https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-73814-7_1
- 3. K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, N.Namashivayam, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, Washington, USA.

- 4. N.Namashivayam, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, Maryland, USA.
 - https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-50995-2_11
- N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015. https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1c6b/9787b0eda7723a14ba6bc92cd77a7dcb0102.pdf
- N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA.
 https://www.computer.org/csdl/proceedings/cluster/2015/6598/00/6598a438.pdf
- 7. N.Namashivayam, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-26428-8_1
- 8. D.Knaak, and N.Namashivayam. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2952638
- 9. N.Namashivayam, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014). https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2676881

KEY ACTIVITIES

1. OpenSHMEM standardization Effort, Participate and represent Cray Inc. in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/

AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. Best Paper Award, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).
- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. Best Undergraduate Student Project, Mepco Schlenk Engineering College, Anna University, India, 2011.